The general steps for using an AED on infants and children are exactly the same as they are for adults,
but there is one very important difference to remember, pad placement.
For infants and children under the age of eight, we use a front and back placement
to ensure the pads do not touch each other on their smaller chests.
You will place one pad directly in the center of the chest, between the nipples,
and the second pad on the back, right between the shoulder blades.
As always, the best way to be sure is to follow the clear graphics printed right on the pads.
Many AEDs are equipped to handle these younger patients.
Some devices come with a specific set of pediatric pads,
while others have a child mode button or a special key you can insert to reduce the energy of the shock.
If the child is eight years old or younger, or weighs less than 55 pounds,
you should always select that child mode or use the pediatric pads if they are available.
However, if you are in an emergency and only have adult pads, it is still okay to use them on a child or infant.
Just be absolutely certain that the pads do not touch or overlap.
One more critical safety rule to remember.
While you can use adult pads on a child in a pinch, you should never use pediatric pads on an adult
because they do not deliver enough energy to be effective.
Once the pads are on, simply continue to listen to the AED.
It will walk you through the analysis and any necessary shocks, just like it did in our adult scenario.